BU Records: Teacher Certification Program Revisions, Inclusive: 1949-1981, undated, Bulk: 1950-1970.
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
BU Records: Teacher Certification Program Revisions
Inclusive: 1949-1981, undated, Bulk: 1950-1970.
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
BU/256
Baylor School of Education
4 document boxes
BU Records: Teacher Certification Program Revisions contains materials related to the reforms made by Baylor University, the School of Education in its teacher certification program in order to meet new state standards.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Excellent.
Biography/Profile
In 1949, the Gilmer-Akins laws were passed which instituted different standards of pay for teachers depending on their level of education. This led many teachers to return to college in order to further their educations. By 1955, a bachelor’s degree was considered the minimum for those seeking certification. As the Texas Educational Agency continued to expand the requirements for certification during the 1950's-1980’s, Baylor University's School of Education (SOE) began to work towards meeting the new state standards. In 1959, the SOE joined the American Association of Colleges of Teacher Organization. It also continued to expand by hiring more faculty, offer professional development to local teachers, integrating the Department of Health, Physical Education, and Recreation into the SOE, and in 1976 moved the school into new facilities located at the Draper Academic Building. Through the 1960s-1970s, the SOE also visited by teams from the Texas Educational Agency who provided feedback and recommendations for their program. By 1975-1976, the SOE had seen 489 graduates become certified through their program. The SOE continues to offer certifications to Baylor education students to this day
Scope and Content
BU Records: Teacher Certification Program Revisions consists of materials such as bulletins, journals, and reports which are dated from 1949-1981 with some undated materials. The records reflect the reforms made by Baylor University, the School of Education to its teacher certification program in order to meet to meet new state standards.
Series I. State Standard consists of bulletins, reports, and guides from the Texas Educational Agency. Series II. Baylor Files consists of reports, bulletins, and publications by Baylor University about its revisions and reforms made to its program.
Arrangement
Prior to processing, the collection was housed in four document boxes. The majority of the files were not in folders and were in unorganized stacks. For the current round of processing, some materials on the same topic were grouped together.
Currently, the collections includes two series: I. State Standards and II. Baylor Files. These series are arranged by date.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. BU/256. Acquired 1985-00-00
Related Resources
Related references
Garrett, Alan W. Garrett. "Teacher Education." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2019 November 26.
“Historical Timeline.” School of Education Centennial - Baylor University. Baylor University School of Education. Accessed 2019 November 26.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- School of Education.; Texas Educational Agency
Subjects
Bulletins.; Education -- Standards -- Texas.; Education -- Texas -- Waco.; Education, Higher -- Texas -- Waco.; Educational law and legislation -- Texas.; Educational tests and measurements.; Handbooks and manuals.; Reports.; Teachers -- Certification -- Texas.
- State Standards, 1949-1978; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Excellent.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains the state publications relating to teacher certification that Baylor University used to revise its program. This series condition is excellent.
  - Senate Bill 116: Minimum Foundation School Law, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Texas Public Schools under the Minimum Foundation Program — An Evaluation, 1949-1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Teacher Supply and Demand in the United States by Ray C. Maul, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bulletin 7: Courses in Professional Elementary Education — Texas Education Agency, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bulletin 573: Teacher Certification in Texas — Texas Education Agency, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bulletin 574: Standards for Teacher Education in Texas — Texas Education Agency, 1955-1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Teacher Certification and Standards for Programs of Teacher Education, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Actions of the State Board of Education and the State Board of Examiners for Teacher Education Affecting Standards for Teacher Education and Certification, 1955-1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bulletin 573: Teacher Certification in Texas — Texas Education Agency, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bulletin 560: Principles and Standards for Accrediting Elementary and Secondary Schools — Texas Education Agency, 1961-1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Principle VII of Principles and Standards for Accrediting Elementary and Secondary Schools — Polices Applicable to Preparation of Teachers Grades 7-12 — Texas Education Agency, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bulletin 651: Standards for Teachers Education in Texas — Texas Education Agency, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - State Plan for Special Education — Texas Education Agency, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Administrative Guide and Handbook for Special Education — Texas Education Agency, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Guidelines for School Personnel: Certifications, Allocations, and Records — Texas Education Agency, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Goals for Public School Education in Texas, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Principles, Standards, and Procedures for the Accreditation of School Districts, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Baylor Files, 1950-1981, undated.; 2
  This series contains the reports made by Baylor University to the Texas Educational Agency on their teacher certification programs. The condition of the series is excellent.
  - Supervision and Guidance Prior to 1955, 1950, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Texas Education Program — Baylor University Report to Texas Education Agency, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Provisional Certificate Programs - Elementary and Secondary, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Texas Education Program — Baylor University Report to Texas Education Agency, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Baylor Program Revisions, 1970-1971, undated. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Texas Education Program — Baylor University Report to Texas Education Agency, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Report of Texas Education Agency Visiting Team - Baylor University (1 of 2), 1970 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Report of Texas Education Agency Visiting Team - Baylor University (2 of 2), 1970 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Educational Specifications for a New Building for School of Education — Baylor University, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Administrator's Certificate Program- School of Education — Baylor University, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Report of the School of Education — Baylor University, October 1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Appendix of the Report of the School of Education — Baylor University, October 1976 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Report of T.E.A Visiting Team, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Bulletin of Baylor University — School of Education, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Education For Living and Making A Living, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 5)